A Guide to the Records of the MCV Foundation/Monumental Church
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Records of the MCV Foundation/Monumental Church 1957-1965
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
2005/Jun/13
2.6 linear feet, 4 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Recieved from David Bagby, Executive Director of the MCV Foundation ca. 1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Monumental Church stands on historic ground. The land was first used in 1786 by the Chevalier Quesnay de Beau Repaire as the location of his Academy of Arts and Sciences. The school only lasted a few years and Quesnay returned to France. One of the buildings that survived was the assembly hall that was quickly converted into the Academy Theatre. It was there that Virginia ratified the Constitution of the United States in 1788. In 1802, the wooden theater caught fire and burned to the ground, but another was erected on its foundation.
This new theater was very popular and often drew large crowds. On December 26, 1811 the theatre was full. During a scene change, a lantern caught the stage backdrop on fire and soon the entire stage was ablaze. In the aftermath of the fire 73 people, mostly women, were killed including Governor George William Smith. The next day a town commission met and resolved to create a memorial to those who died on the theaters grounds. Monumental Church became this memorial.
Two heroes who emerged from the inferno were blacksmith and slave Gilbert Hunt and Dr. James McCaw, a Richmond physician (and grandfather of Dr. James B. McCaw, namesake of the Tompkins-McCaw Library at Virginia Commonwealth University).
Opened in 1814 the Church was built on land "for ever kept sacred". In a vault under the church lay the bodies of those who perished that night, and several plaques and memorials line the churches walls. Chief Justice John Marshall was instrumental in the initial phases in creating this Greek revival church. And after it opened, Marshall was a congregation member. Designed by Roberts Mills, Monumental is the only surviving Church Mills designed with its dome intact. The church was known as Monumental Episcopal Church.
As the City of Richmond grew so did the Medical College of Virginia, taking up most of the city plots around the Church. Under an agreement with Virginia Commonwealth University the Church became a religious center for the student body supplementing its own congregation in 1958. After a major renovation phase of the Church that began in 1960, the Episcopal diocese found the cost too high and moved the congregation to a newer building in 1965. Ownership transferred to the University who attempted to continue the renovations. The Church was listed on National Registry of Historic Places in 1971. The University gave Monumental Church to the Historic Richmond Foundation in 1983, and they began a series of restorative projects that are ongoing.
Scope and Content
The Collection includes minutes of the Monumental Church Endowment, correspondence with J. Ambler Johnston who oversaw the early renovation. Also included are clippings and articles relating to the Church and its members. The Collection focuses on the time of its first renovation from 1960-1965. It does not cover activity of the congregation or of the years of University ownership.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- History of Monumental Church (Box-folder 1)
  - Historical Accounts, Rev. A. Ronald Merrick 1901-1981 (Box-folder 1.1)
    This folder contains photocopied Church programs, papers written about the history of the Church, and several retyped newspaper articles collected by the last rector of the Church. Also included are the following:
    - A Brief Historical Sketch of The Monumental Church 1924 (Box-folder 1.1)
      by Mary Newton Stanard
    - Monumental Church Issue 1966 (Box-folder 1.1)
      Bulletin, Medical College of Virginia, Vol. LXII, No. 4
    - The First Academy 1966 (Box-folder 1.1)
      by Samuel J. Gamble, The Virginia Journal of Science, Vol. 17, No. 1, 1966
  - Rev. A. Ronald Merrick, Contents of Envelope from W. T. Sanger's Office 1911-1963 (Box-folder 1.2)
    This folder contains papers, articles and clippings saved by Dr. Sanger and given to Merrick. Included are lists of parishioners in military service, clippings, a theatre bill, an artist rendition of downtown Richmond, and a Church program.
  - History of Monumental Church, newspaper clippings 1933-1966 (Box-folder 1.3)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings and other articles on the history of the Monumental Church.
  - History of Monumental Church, Rev. George Ossman (Box-folder 1.4)
    This folder contains historical articles and clippings collected during Ossman's time as rector. In addition to clippings and articles, the following items are included
    - "In Old Virginia" 02 Dec, 1945 (Box-folder 1.4)
      Transcript for radio program on WLEE
    - "The Chaplaincy At The Medical College of Virginia" 1945 (Box-folder 1.4)
      Virginia Medical Monthly, Vol. 72
    - "An Address delivered in Connection with the Unveiling of the Moore, Marshall, and Fisher Memorial Windows" 1901 (Box-folder 1.4)
      Rev. W. E. Evans.
    - "Monumental Church, 13th Annual Discourse" 5 Dec. 1875 (Box-folder 1.4)
      Address given that anniversary Sunday.
- Monumental Church Endowment Fund, Inc 1911-1965 (Box-folder 2)
  - Board of Management Minutes 1911-1926, 1933-1947, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Board of Management Minutes 1960-1965 (Box-folder 2.2)
- Correspondence, J. Ambler Johnston. 1954-1965 (Box-folder 3)
  This series contains the correspondence concerning J. Ambler Johnston of Carneal and Johnson architectural firm. Johnston was also a member of the Monumental's congregation. These papers cover topics including bids and contracts, vendor relations, budgetary issues and other business contacts.
  - Folder A 1954-1963 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Folder B 1954-1963 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Folder A 1963-1965 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Folder B 1963-1965 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Folder A 1965
  - Correspondence between Johnston and MCV Officials 1926-1970 (Box-folder 3.6)
    "Sundry Papers Incident to Transfer to Medical College Foundation."
  - Address given by Johnston at Monumental Church rededication 1965
- Correspondence by topic (Box-folder 4)
  - Paintings and pictures, Teusler Hall 1958-1961 (Box-folder 4.1)
  - Monumental Church, handrails. A. Ronald Merrick 1961 (Box-folder 4.2)
  - Monumental Church, windows. A. Ronald Merrick, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 4.3)
  - Monumental Church, Restoration Fund 1963-1965 (Box-folder 4.4)
  - Monumental Church, miscellaneous documents. (Box-folder 4.5)
    This folder contains product brochures, an outline specification, and a report on costs and objectives.
- Committee Records; Religious Activities Committee, Monumental Church Property Committee 1976-1978 (Box-folder 5)
  This series contains the records of these committees, correspondence and articles. Also included are the following:
  - "Monumental Church, A History" February, 1976 (Box-folder 5)
    VCU Magazine
  - List of items found in the Church belonging to the Episcopal Diocese of Virginia. (Box-folder 5)
    Items on list included baptismry bowls, religious ornamentation and vestments.
  - Program from the Re-Opening Ceremony 5 November, 1978 (Box-folder 5)
- Architectural Plans and Proposals 1961-1977 (Box-folder 6)
  This series contains several plans and proposals for Richmond, Virginia Commonwealth University, and Monumental Church
  - "Outline Specification for the Preservation of the Monumental Church" January 1961 (Box-folder 6.1)
  - "A Study of the Architectural Preservation Potential of the VCU Academy Campus" 1970 (Box-folder 6.2)
    This folder contains photographs and blueprints by Virginia Historic Landmark Commission.
  - "200 Block of Franklin Street, A Statement of Circumstances and Objectives." 1974 (Box-folder 6.3)
    by Virginia Landmark Corporation
  - Robert Winthrup 1974-1978 (Box-folder 6.4)
    This folder contains files regarding Robert Winthrup, architect from Glave, Newman, Anderson.
  - "Adaptive Preservation Study for the Monumental Church" 1974 (Box-folder 6.5)
    by Glave, Newman, Anderson.
  - "Eleven Projects in Adaptive Preservation." (Box-folder 6.6)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified. (Box-folder 6.7)
- Blueprints (Box-folder 7)
  - Folder A 1966-1967 (Box-folder 7.1)
  - Folder B 1976-1977 (Box-folder 7.2)